Dan Whiting

(202) 531-9091 · dan@danwhiting.com · @danwhiting

SUMMARY

Over the past 19 years, worked in public policy, communications, and marketing, including strategic planning, management, media relations, legislative, writing, website development, video production, project/product management, budgeting, and new business development. This includes 11 years in the U.S. Senate and time as a Presidential appointee at USDA. This breadth of experience brings a unique understanding to customer, business, and team needs.

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

Strategy

- Developed strategic and crisis communication plans, including the foundational plan for the National Alliance of Forest Owners.
- Managed the strategic direction and execution of a successful six-state grassroots/grasstops advocacy campaign with a \$1M+ budget.
- Built coalitions with partners to advance shared interests, including one of wildlife conservation, hunting, and fishing groups to renew key federal legislation.

Media Relations

- Outreached and pitched stories to national, regional, local, and trade press, from the *Wall Street Journal* to *Energy and Environment Daily*.
- Developed relationships with key reporters and editors.
- Wrote press releases and pitch e-mails.
- Taught media relations seminars for the Leadership Institute and other groups.
- Coordinated crisis communications for a U.S. Senator and an organization with kidnapped workers in Afghanistan.
- Monitored media coverage and adjusted strategy and tactics based on results.

Public Policy

- Advised U.S. Senator on energy, natural resources, environment, agriculture, public lands, and appropriations.
- Wrote talking points, speeches, memos, regulatory comments, letters, and white papers.
- Lobbied Congress and the Obama Administration.
- Monitored implementation of the 2008 Farm Bill at the USDA Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS).
- Enacted President Bush's priorities at NRCS.

[continued]

Messaging/Writing

- Managed brand and messaging research, development, and testing.
- Wrote press releases, op-eds, letters-to-the-editor, blog entries, web content, scripts, white papers, fact sheets, brochures, and ad copy.
- Summarized key finds of academic reports to be easily understood by decision makers, reporters, and the public.
- Wrote proposals for new business.
- Presented content marketing workshops.

Internal Communications

- Orchestrated awareness campaigns to include web, e-mail, posters, messaging, and briefings for a worldwide audience of over one million people.
- Designed and wrote e-learning courses for worldwide organizations.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Communications, Marketing, and Government Relations Consultant 2016-Present

ADG Creative

Senior Strategist	2011-2016

National Alliance of Forest Owners

Director of Communications	2009-2011
Director or Communications	2007 2011

USDA Natural Resources Conservation Service

	0000 0000
Chief of Staff	2008-2009
CHELOLOIGI	/ ()()()-/ ()() /

Asian Rural Life Development Association

Crisis Spokesman	2008

U.S. Senator Larry Craig 1997-2008

Communications Director, 2006-2008

Press Secretary, 2004-2006

Regional Director, North Idaho, 2001-2004

Legislative Assistant, 1999-2001

Legislative Correspondent, 1997-1999

EDUCATION

MA	Management and Entrepreneurship	Regent University
BS	Human Resource Management	University of Idaho
Certificate	Front End Web Development	General Assembly

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

Pro Bono Consultant, Taproot Foundation	2016-Present
Instructor for Media Relations and Writing, Leadership Institute	2006-2008